<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A remonstrance and declaration of the Generall Assembly of the Church of Scotland, concerning present and imminent dangers, and concerning duties relating thereto.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79754</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4252</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E569_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206279</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865451</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865451</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117692</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79754)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117692)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 87:E569[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A remonstrance and declaration of the Generall Assembly of the Church of Scotland, concerning present and imminent dangers, and concerning duties relating thereto.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Edinburgh, printed by Evan Tyler, printer to the Kings most excellent Majesty, 1649. And re-printed at London for Robert Bostock, dwelling at the sign of the Kings-head in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 14".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117692:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REMONSTRANCE AND DECLARATION OF THE Generall Aſſembly OF THE Church of Scotland, <hi>CONCERNING</hi> Preſent and Imminent Dangers, and concerning Duties relating thereto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty, 1649.</p>
            <p>And Re-printed at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>Robert Boſtock,</hi> dwelling at the ſign of the Kings-head in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117692:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117692:2"/>
            <head>Edinburgh, <date>27. <hi>July,</hi> 1649.</date> 
               <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 27.</head>
            <head>A ſeaſonable and neceſſary Warning and Declaration, concerning Preſent and Imminent Dangers, and concerning Duties relating thereto, from the General Aſſembly of this Kirk, unto all the Members thereof.</head>
            <p>THe Lord, who chooſes <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in a furnace of Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hath been pleaſed, ſince the beginning of the work of <hi>Reformation</hi> in this Land, to exerciſe his People with many tryals: All that deſired to keep a good conſcience, were not long ago under many heavy and ſad preſſures from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolency and oppreſſion of a prevailing party of diſ-affected and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant men, who under a pretext of bringing the King to a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Honor, Freedom, and Safety,</hi> did carry on an unlawful En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement againſt the Kingdom of <hi>England:</hi> and if the Lord had not been merciful unto his People, they were like either to have been baniſhed out of the Land, or to have bin kept in a perpetual bondage in their <hi>conſciences, perſons, and eſtates:</hi> But he, whoſe Meſſengers thoſe men had mocked, and whoſe Word they had deſpiſed, did bring them down ſuddenly in a day, and reſtored <hi>liberty and peace unto his people,</hi> a mercy and deliverance, which as it ought to be remembred with thankfulneſs and praiſe, ſo may it engage our hearts not to faint in troubles and ſtraits that do yet abide us, but to truſt in the name of the Lord, who both can and will deliver us ſtill out of all our afflictions.</p>
            <p>Albeit, we do now enjoy many rich and precious bleſſings where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we have reaſon to be comforted and to rejoyce; yet it were to ſhut our eyes if we ſhould not ſee our ſelvs involved in, &amp; threatned with many and great dangers at home and from abroad. It is mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of exceeding great ſorrow to think upon the ignorance and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanity, the impenitency and ſecurity that abounds ſtill in the Land, notwithſtanding all the gracious diſpenſation of the Goſpel and means of grace in ſuch purity and plenty, that none of the Nations round about us can boaſt of the like, and of all the long-ſuffering patience of the Lord, and of all his ſharp rods wherewith he hath af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted us from year to year, and of all the mercies and deliverances wherewith he hath viſited us, and of our late ſolemn confeſſion of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117692:3"/>ſins, andengagement unto duties, ſealed with the renewing of the Covenant and the Oath of God; Which ſome men have ſo far al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready forgotten, as to return with the dog to the vomit, and with the ſow to the puddle; and many ſigns of inconſtancy and levity do appear among all ſorts and ranks of perſons, who ſeem to want no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a ſuitable tentation to draw them away from their ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſs: Our Army is not yet ſufficiently purged, but there be ſtill in it Malignant and ſcandalous men, whoſe fidelity and conſtancy, as it is much to be doubted, ſo is the wrath of the Lord to be feared, upon their proceedings and undertakings, without a ſpeedy and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual remedy.</p>
            <p>That prevailing party of Sectaries in <hi>England,</hi> who have broken the Covenant, and deſpiſed the Oath of God, corrupted the Truth, ſubverted the ſundamental Government by King and Parliament, and taken away the Kings life, look upon us with an evill eye, as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe who ſtand in the way of their monſtrous and new-fangled devices in Religion and Government; and though there were no cauſe to fear any thing from that party but the Gangrene and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of thoſe many damnable and abominable errors, which have taken hold on them, yet our vicinity unto, and dayly commerce with that Nation, may juſtly make us afraid that the Lord may give up many in this Land unto a ſpirit of deluſion, to beleeve lyes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have not received the love of the Truth.</p>
            <p>Neither is the Malignant party ſo far broken and brought low, as that they have abandoned all hopes of carrying on their former deſigns againſt the Covenant and work of Reformation, beſide ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them in this Kingdom who are as Foxes tyed in chains, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their evil nature, and waiting an opportunity to break their cords, and again to prey upon the Lords people. There be ſtanding Armies in <hi>Ireland,</hi> under the command of the Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond,</hi> the Lord <hi>Inchiqueen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the Lord of <hi>Airds,</hi> and <hi>George Munroe,</hi> who forgetting all the horrible cruelty that was exerciſed by the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Rebels upon many thouſands of the Engliſh and Scottiſh Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in that Land, have entred into a Peace and Aſſociation with them, that they may the more eaſily carry on the old deſigns of the Popiſh, Prelatical and Malignant party, and the Lord of <hi>Airds,</hi> and <hi>George Monroe,</hi> have by treachery and oppreſſion brought the Province of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> and Gariſons therein, under their power and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and have redacted our Country-men, and ſuch as adhere un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Covenant and cauſe of God in that Province, unto many
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117692:3"/>
               <hi>miſeries and ſtraits,</hi> and are like to baniſh the <hi>Miniſters of the Gospel,</hi> and to overturn theſe fair beginnings of the work of God, which were unto many a branch of hope, that the Lord meant to make <hi>Ireland</hi> a pleaſant Land.</p>
            <p>But which is more grievous unto us then all theſe, our King, Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding of the Lords hand, againſt his Fathers oppoſition to the work of God, and of the many ſad and doleful conſequences that followed thereupon, in reference to Religion and his Subjects and Perſon, and Government, doth hearken unto the counſels of theſe, who were Authors of theſe miſeries unto his Royal Father, and to his Kingdoms, by which it hath come to paſs, that his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty hath hitherto refuſed to grant the juſt and neceſſary deſires of this Kirk and Kingdom, which were tendred unto him from the Commiſſioners of both for ſecuring of Religion, the Liberties of the Subject, his Majeſties Government, and the Peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; And it is much to be feared that thoſe wicked Counſellors may ſo far prevail upon him in his tender years, as to engage him in a war, for overturning (if it be poſſible) of the work of God, and bearing down all thoſe in the three Kingdoms that adhere thereto, which if he ſhall do, cannot but bring great wrath from the Lord upon himſelf and his throne, and muſt be the cauſe of many new, and great miſeries, and calamities to theſe lands.</p>
            <p>It concerns a Nation thus ſinful and loaden with iniquity, and involved in ſo many difficulties and dangers, by timous repentance and unfained humiliation to draw neer to God, and to wreſtle with him in Prayer and ſupplication, that our ſin may be pardoned, and our iniquity done away, and that he would eſtabliſh the Land in the love of the Truth, and inable every one in their ſtation to do their duty boldly and without fear, and in a humble dependance upon the Lord, in whom alone is the ſalvation of his people; every man ought with all faithfulneſs and diligence, to make uſe of all theſe meanes that are approved and allowed of God, for preſerving and carrying on of his work, and for ſecuring and guarding the Land againſt all enemies whatſoever, both upon the right hand and upon the left.</p>
            <p>The Spirit of errour and deluſion in our Neighbour-Land, in the policy of Satan hath vailed it ſelfe in many, under the mask of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and is in the righteous and wiſe diſpenſation of God, armed with power and attended with ſucceſſe. Therefore all the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of this Land would labour for more knowledge, and more love of the truth, without which they may eaſily be deceived, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117692:4"/>led into tentation, and would learn to diſtinguiſh betwixt the ſhew and power of godlineſs; We know that there be many in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> who be truly godly, and mourn with us for all the errors and abominations that are in that land, but it is without controverſie, that that Spirit which hath acted in the Courſes and Counſels of theſe who hath retarded and obſtructed the work of God, deſpiſed the Covenant, forced the Parliament, murthered the King, changed the civil Government, and eſtabliſhed ſo vaſt a tolleration in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, cannot be the Spirit of Righteouſneſs and Holineſs, becauſe it teaches not men to live godly and righteouſly, but draws them a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ide into error, and makes them to bring forth the bitter fruits of inipiety and imquity, and therefore ought to be avoided; and not only are ſuch of our Nation as travel in our Neighbour-land, to take heed unto themſelves, that they receive not infection from ſuch as are leavened with Errour, but theſe alſo who live at home, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in thoſe places where Sectaries, upon pretext of merchandiſe, and other civil imployments, ordinarily traffique and converſe: Neither needs any man to be affraid of the power and ſucceſſe of that party, they who have gadded about ſo much to change their way, ſhall ere long be aſhamed; the Lord hath rejected their confidences, and they ſhall not proſper in them. How far they may proceed in their Reſolutions and Actings againſt this Kingdom, is in the hand of the moſt high, if the Lord ſhall ſuffer that party to invade this Land, it may be the comfort and incouragement of all the Inhabitants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that not only hath that unlawfull engagement againſt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>England</hi> been declared againſt, and condemned both by Kirk and State, but alſo that theſe men can pretend no quarrel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, unleſſe it be that we have adhered unto the Solemn Leagne and Covenant, from which they have ſo foully revolted and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlidden, and that we have born teſtimony againſt Tolleration, and their proceedings in reference to Religion and Government, and the taking away of the Kings life; and therefore we truſt that in ſuch a caſe none will be ſo far deficient in their duty as not to defend themſelves againſt ſuch injuſt violence, and in the ſtrength of the Lord to adhere unto their former principles, with much boldneſs of ſpirit, and willingneſs of heart, in this certainly we ſhall have a good conſcience, and the Lord ſhall be with us.</p>
            <p>We are not ſo, to have the one of our eyes upon the Sectaries, as not to hold the other upon the Malignants, they being an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my more numerous, and no leſs ſubtile and powerful nor the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117692:4"/>and at this time more dangerous unto us, not only becauſe experience hath proven that there is a greater aptitude and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in theſe of our Land, to comply with Malignants then Sectaries, that they carry on their wicked deſigns under a pretext of being for the King, but alſo becauſe there be many of them in our own bowels, and for that they do pretend to be for mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Kings Perſon and Authority, (and which is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of our grief) becauſe the King owns their principles and ways, which if it be not taken heed unto, may prove a great ſnare and dangerous tentation to many to ſide with them againſt the Lords people, and his cauſe. The conſtant tenor of the carriage of theſe in this Land, who ſtand for the cauſe of God, are undenya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble arguments of their affection to Monarchy, and to that Royal Family and Line which hath ſweyed the Scepter of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for many hundreds of yeers paſt, albeit his Majeſty, who lately reigned, refuſed to harken to their juſt deſires, yet did they with much patience and moderation of mind, ſupplicate and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licite his Majeſty for ſatisfaction in theſe things that conceres Religion and the Covenant, and were ſtill willing, that upon ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction given, he ſhould be admitted to the exerciſe of his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and whatſoever envy and malice objects to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were careful to get aſſurance concerning the ſafety of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Perſon, when they brought their Army out of <hi>England,</hi> and when notwithſtanding of that aſſurance, the prevailing par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Sectaries were acting his life, did to the utmoſt of their power, endevor by their Commiſſioners that there might have been no ſuch proceeding, and when their deſires and endevors were not ſucceſsful, did proteſt and bear teſtimony againſt the ſame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And as both Kirk and State had teſtified their tender re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to his Majeſty who now reigns, by their Letters written to him whilſt his Father was yet living, ſo no ſooner did the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hear of his Fathers death, but they did with all ſolemnity proclaim him King of theſe Kingdoms, and after they had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted his Majeſty by Meſſages with their proceedings herein, Commiſſioners were ſent both from State and Kirk, inſtructed with power and commiſſion, to expreſſe the Affection of this Kingdom to Monarchy, and his Majeſties Perſon and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, together with their deſires concerning the ſecurity of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the Pence of thoſe Kingdoms. And albeit the deſires of both which are now publiſhed to the world, with his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117692:5"/>Anſwers thereto, are ſuch as are moſt juſt and neceſſary; yet the Counſels of the Malignant party had ſo great influence upon his Majeſty, that his Anſwers are not only not ſatisfactory, but ſhort of that which was many times granted by his Royal Father, and cannot be acquieſced unto unleſs we would abandon the League and Covenant, and betray Religion, and the cauſe of God.</p>
            <p>We hold it the duty of all who live in this Land, to wreſtle with God in the behalf of the King, that he may be recovered out of the ſnare of evil Counſel, and brought to give ſatisfaction to the publick deſires of Kirk and State; and in their places and ſtations, to uſe all endevors with himſelf and others for that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and to be willing, upon ſatisfaction given, to admit him to the exerciſe of his power and cheerfully to obey him in all things according to the Will of God, and the Laws of the Kingdom, and to do every thing that tends to the preſervation of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Perſon, and juſt greatneſs and Authority, in the defence and preſervation of the true Religion and Liberties of the Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>But if his Majeſty, or any having or pretending power and commiſſion from him, ſhall invade this Kingdom, upon pretext of eſtabliſhing him in the exerciſe of his Royal Power, as it will be an high provocat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on againſt God to be acceſſory or aſſiſting thereto, ſo w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll it be a neceſſary duty to reſiſt and oppoſe the ſame. We know that many are ſo forgetful of the Oa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h of God, and ignorant and careleſs of the Intereſt of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Goſpel, and doth ſo little tender that which concerns his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the Priviledges thereof, and doth ſo much dote upon abſolute and Arbitrary Government for gaining their own ends, and ſo much malign the Inſtruments of the work of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they would admit his Majeſty to the exerciſe of his Royal Power upon any terms whatſoever, though with never ſo much prejudice to Religion, and the Liberties of theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, would think it quarrel enough to make War upon all thoſe who for conſcience ſake cannot condeſcend thereto; but we deſire all theſe who fear the Lord, and mind to keep their Covenant impartially to conſider theſe things which follows.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That as Magiſtrates and their power is ordained of GOD, ſo are they in the exerciſe thereof, not to walk according to their own will, but according to the Law of Equity and Righteouſneſs, as being the Miniſters of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117692:5"/>of God for the ſafety of his People; Therefore a boundleſſe and illimited power is to be acknowledged in no King nor Magiſtrate; neither is our King to be admitted to the exerciſe of his power as long as he refuſes to walk in the Adminiſtration of the ſame according to this rule, and the eſtabliſhed Laws of the kingdom, that his Subjects may live under him a quiet and peaceable life, in all godlineſſe and honeſty.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is a mutuall obligation and ſtipulation betwixt the King and his People; as both of them are tyed to God, ſo each of them are tyed one to another for the performance of mutuall and reciprocal duties: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this, it is ſtatute and ordained in the eighth Act of the firſt Parliament of <hi>King James</hi> the ſixth, That all Kings, Princes or Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates whatſomever, holding their place, which hereafter ſhall happen in any time to Reign and bear rule over this Realm, at the time of their Coronation and receit of their Princely Authority, make their faithfull promiſe by Oath in the preſence of the eternall God, that during the whole courſe of their lives, they ſhall ſerve the eternal God to the utmoſt of their power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> according as he hath required in his moſt holy Word, contained in the old &amp; new Teſtament; and according to the ſame Word, ſhall maintain the true Religion of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> the preaching of his moſt holy Word, and due and right Adminiſtration of his Sacraments now received and preached within this Realm, and ſhall aboliſh and gainſtand all falſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion contrary to the ſame, and ſhall rule the people committed to their charge according to the will and command of God revealed in his Word, and according to the lovable Laws and conſtitutions received within this Realm, and ſhall procure to the utmoſt of their power, to the Kirk of God, and whole Chriſtian People, true and perfect peace in all time coming, and that Juſtice and Equity be kept to all creatures without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception: which Oath was ſworn firſt by King <hi>Iames</hi> the 6, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by King <hi>Charles</hi> at his coronation, and is inſerted in our National <hi>Covenant,</hi> which was approven by the King who lately reigned: As long therefore as his Majeſty who now reigns, refuſes to hearken to the juſt and neceſſary deſires of State and Kirk, propounded to his Majeſty for the ſecurity of Religion, and ſafety of his People, and to engage and oblige himſelf for the performance of his duty to his people: It is conſonant to Scripture, and Reaſon, and the Laws of the kingdom, that they ſhould refuſe to admit him to the exerciſe of his Government, untill he give ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in theſe things.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the League and Covenant, which hath been ſo ſolemnly ſworn and renewed by this kingdom, the duty of defending and preſerving the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117692:6"/>Kings Majeſties Perſon and Authority is joyned with, and ſubordinate unto the duty of preſerving and defending the true Religion and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the kingdoms: And therefore his Majeſty ſtanding in oppoſition to the juſt and neceſſary publick deſires concerning Religion and Liberties, it were a manifeſt breach of covenant, and a preferring of the Kings intereſt to the intereſt of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to bring him to the exerciſe of his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all power; which he, walking in a contrary way, and being compaſſed about with Malignant counſels, cannot but imploy unto the prejudice and ruin of both.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Was not an arbitrary Government and unlimited power the fountain of moſt of all the corruptions both in Kirk and State? And was it not for reſtraint of this, and for their own juſt defence againſt Tyranny and unjuſt Violence, which ordinarily is the fruit and effect of ſuch a power, that the Lords people did joyn in covenant, and have been at the expence of ſo much blood, pains, and treaſure theſe yeers paſt? And if his Majeſty ſhould be admitted to the exerciſe of his Government before ſatisfaction given, were it not to put in his hand that arbitrary power which we have upon juſt and neceſſary grounds been ſo long withſtanding; and ſo to abandon our former principles, and betray out Cauſe?</p>
            <p n="5">5. The King being averſe from the work of Reformation and the Inſtruments thereof, and compaſſed about with Malignant and diſaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted men, whom he hearkens unto as his moſt faithfull Counſellers, and looks upon as his beſt and moſt Loyall Subjects: We leave to all indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent men to judge, whether his Majeſty, being admitted to the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of his power before ſatisfaction given, would not by ſuch counſels endeavour an overturning of the things which God hath wrought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and labour to draw publick adminiſtrations concerning Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the Liberties of the Subject, unto that courſe and channel in which they did run under Prelacy, and before the work of Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Which we have the more cauſe to fear, becauſe his Royall Father did ſo often declare, that he conceived himſelf bound to imploy all the power that God ſhould put in his hands to the utmoſt for theſe ends; and that he adheres as yet to his Fathers principles, and walks in his way, and hath made a peace with the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels, by which is granted unto them the full liberty of Popery.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It is no ſtrange nor new thing for Kingdoms to preſerve Religion and themſelves from ruine, by putting reſtraint upon the exerciſe of the power and Government of thoſe who have refuſed to grant thoſe things
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117692:6"/>that were neceſſary for the good of Religion and the Peoples ſafety; there have been many Precedents of it in this and other Nations of old, and of late upon theſe and other important conſiderations: It ſhall bee the wiſedom of every one who dwells in the Land, to take heed of ſuch a temptation and ſnare, that they be not acceſſary to any ſuch deſigns or endeavours; as they would not bring upon themſelves, and upon their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies the guilt of all the detriment that will undoubtedly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thereupon to Religion and the Covenant, and of all the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and calamities that it will bring upon his Majeſties Perſon and throne, and upon theſe Kingdoms; ſuch a thing would in all appearance be the undermining and ſhaking, if not the overthrowing and deſtroying of the work of Reformation; and therefore whoſoever attempt the ſame, oppoſe themſelves to the cauſe of God, and will at laſt daſh againſt the Rock of the Lords power, which hath broken in pieces many high and lofty ones ſince the beginning of this Work in theſe Kingdoms, and it is unto us a ſure Word of promiſe, That whoſoever ſhall aſſociate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or toke counſell together, or gird themſelves againſt God and his Work, ſhall be broken in pieces.</p>
            <p>It is not only joyning in Arms with the Malignant partie, that all theſe who would keep their integrity has need to beware of, but alſo ſubtill devices and deſignes that are promoted by fair pretexts and perſwaſions to draw men to diſpence at leaſt with ſome part of theſe neceſſary deſires that are propounded to his Majeſtie for ſecuring of Religion after many turnings and deviſes the foundation of the Unlawfull Engagement was at laſt laid by his Majeſties Conceſſions of the date the yeer 1648. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in though many things ſeemed to be granted, yet that was denied, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which Religion and the Union betwixt the Kingdoms could not have been ſecured, and it is probable that ſuch a way may be aſſayed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and proſecuted with very much cunning and skill to deceive and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare the ſimple: It doth therefore concern all ranks and conditions of perſons to be the more warie and circumſpect, eſpecially in that which concerns the Nationall Covenant, and the ſolemn League and Covenant, that before his Majeſtie be admitted to the exerciſe of his Royall Power, that by and after the Oath of Coronation, he ſhall aſſure and declare by his Solemn Oath under his hand and ſeal, his allowance of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Covenant, and of the Solemn League and Covenant, and obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to proſecute the ends thereof in his Station and Calling, and that he ſhall for himſelf and ſucceſſors, conſent and agree to Acts of Parliament, injoyning the ſolemn League and Covenant, and fully eſtabliſhing Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteriall
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117692:7"/>Government, the Dire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tory of Worſhip, the Confeſſion of Faith and Catechiſme, as they are approvea by the Generall Aſſembly of this Kirk and Parliament of this Kingdom, in all his Majeſties Dominions, and that he ſhall obſerve theſe in his own practiſe and familie, and that he ſhall never made oppoſition to any of theſe, nor endeavour any change thereof; Albeit the League and Covenant be deſpiſed by that prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing party in <hi>England,</hi> and the work of Uniformity, thorow the retard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and obſtructions that have come in the way, be almoſt forgotten by theſe Kingdome, yet the obligation of that Covenant is perpetuall, and all the duties contained therein are conſtantly to be minded, and proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by every one of us, and our poſterity, according to their place and ſtations; and therefore we are no leſſe zealouſly to endeavour, that his Majeſtie may Eſtabliſh, and ſwear and ſubſcribe the ſame, then if it were unanimouſly regarded and ſtuck unto by all the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> his Majeſte ſwearing and ſubſcribing the league and Covenant, will much contribute for the Security of Religion, his Majeſties happineſs, and the Peace of his Kingdoms</p>
            <p>As it is incumbent to all, who live in this Kirk and Kingdom to bee watchfull and circumſpect, ſo it concernes theſe of the High and Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Court of Parliament and their Committees, in a ſpecial way to ſee to their dutie, and to be ſtraight and reſolute in the performance of the ſame: Their former proceedings is unto us a ſufficient evidence and ground of hope, that they will not be wanting in any neceſſary teſtimonie of duty and Loyaltie that they owe to the King, by uſing all juſt and ſeaſonable eſtabliſhed upon his Thrones; And we truſt, that upon the other hand, the ſenſe of their Obligation to God; and his Oath that is upon them, will make them conſtantly to adhere to their former principles, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions and deſires concerning Religion and the Covenant, that reall ſatisfaction may be had there anent, before the King be put in exerciſe of his power, and that they wil carefully provide for the ſafety of the Kingdom, both in regard of inteſtine dangers, and in regard of invaſion from without: It is not long ſince they, together with the reſt of the Land, made ſolemn publike Confeſſion of Compliance with Malignants, carnall confidence, following of it ſelf intereſts, and hearkning to the Counſels of fleſh and blood, and did in a ſpecial way engage themſelves to comply, and ſeek themſelves and their own things, no more to abandon the counſels of their own hearts, and not to rely upon the Arm of fleſh and to purge Judicatories, and Armies from prophane, and ſcandalous
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117692:7"/>Perſons; And God forbid that they ſhould ſo ſoon forget, or neglect ſo neceſſary duties, and fall again unto ſo great and grievous tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. We truſt that they will ſeek the things of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and not their own things, that they will hearken to his Word, and not walk in the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations of their own hearts, that they will relie upon the Arm of the Lord, and not upon the arm of fleſh, that they will be warie and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect in diſcerning the diſpoſitions and affections of thoſe whom they put in truſt; and that ſeeing this Kindom hath ſo much ſmarted, and been ſo often deceived by compliance with Malignants, that they will care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully avoid this ſnare of thoſe who were upon the former Unlawful En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, and be tender in bringing in of ſuch; And we cannot but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort them in the Name of the Lord, to take notice of the Oppreſſion of the People and Commons in the Land, by the lawleſſe exactions of Land-Lords, Collectors and Souldiers. We doe not juſtifie the murmurings and grudgings of thoſe, who preferring the things of the world to the Goſpel and things of Jeſus Chriſt, repine at neceſſarie burthens, without which it is not poſſible that the Land can be ſecured from invaſion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and inſurrection within, or the Cauſe and People of God defended from enemies: It is the duty of every one who hath taken the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, willingly and with a cheerful minde to beſtow their meanes and their pains as they ſhall be called thereunto in an orderly way; yet ſhould theſe to whom God hath committed the Government, take care that they be not nedleſly burthened, and that none grind their faces by oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; not only by making of Laws againſt the ſame, but by ſearching out of the cauſe of the poor, and by executing thoſe Laws timouſly upon theſe that oppreſſe them, that they may find real redreſſe of their juſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances and complaints, and be encouraged to bear thoſe burthens which cannot be avoided.</p>
            <p>As the Parliament have begun, ſo we hope they will continue, to purge out all theſe from truſt, that are not of known integrity and affection to the cauſe of God, and of a blameleſs and Chriſtian converſation, and that they, and the Officers of the Army in their reſpective places, will ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly minde and ſpeedily and reſolutely goe about the removing from the Army all malignant and ſcandalous perſons, and alſo the removing of Sectaries, when any ſhall be found therein; that they may give reall evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that they did not deal deceitfully with God, in the day that they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged themſelves thereto.</p>
            <p>Albeit we hope and pray that thoſe who bear charge in our Army, will from the remembrance of the Lords goodneſs to them, and the honour
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117692:8"/>that he hath put upon them, endevour to carry themſelves faithfully and ſtraightly, yet it cannot be unſeaſonable to warm them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke heed of tentations, and to beware of ſnares, that they be not drawn to indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency or neutrality in the cauſe of God, much leſſe into connivance at, or compliance with the courſes and deſignes of malignants or Sectaries, but to ſtick cloſely by the ſame, and to be zealous againſt all the enemies and adverſaries thereof, and it concerns Souldiers to be content with their wages, and to doe violence to no man, but as they are called unto the defence of the cauſe and people of God, ſo to behave themſelves in ſuch a blameleſs and Chriſtian a way, that their carriage may be a teſtimony to his cauſe, and a comfort to his people, ſo ſhall our Armies proſper and the Lord ſhall goe out with them.</p>
            <p>But moſt of all it concerns the Miniſters of the Goſpel, whom God hath called to give warning to his people to look to their duty, It is unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably true, that may of the evils wherewith this Kirk and Kingdom hath been afflicted in our age, have come to paſſe, becauſe of the negligence of ſome, and corruptions of others of the Miniſtry, whilſt ſome fell aſleep, and were careleſs, and others were covetous and ambitious, the evil man brought in Prelacy and the Ceremonies, and hah facre promoted the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice Book, and the Book of Cannon, and the courſe of backſliding and revolting was carried on, untill it pleaſed God to ſtirre up the ſpirits of theſe few who had ſtood in the gap to oppoſe and reſiſt the ſame, and to begin the work of Reformation in the Land; ſince which time the ſilence of ſome Miniſters, and complyance of others, hath had great influence up. on the backſliding of many amongſt the people, who upon the diſcovery of the evill of their way, complain that they got not warning, or that if they were warned by ſome, others held their peace, or did juſtifie them in the courſe of their back-ſliding; We can look upon ſuch Miniſters no otherwiſe, then upon thoſe that are guilty of the blood of the Lords people, and with whom the Lord will reckon for all the breach of Covenant, and defection that hath been in the Land. The Prieſts lips ſhould preſerve knowledge, and they ſhould ſeek the Law at his mouth, for he is the meſſenger of the Lord of Hoſts; but ſuch have departed out of the way, and have cauſed many to ſtumble at the Law, therefore hath the Lord made them contemptible and baſe before all the people, according as they have not kept his wayes, but have been partial in his Law; becauſe they have loſt their ſavour, he hath caſt out many of them as unſavoury ſalt; but ſuch as have been faithfull, as he hath preſerved them from the violence and fury of men, ſo hath he verified his word in their mouths,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117692:8"/>both againſt his enemies, and concerning his people, and his work, and makes them ſee (though not all their deſires concerning the Goſpel, and the work of God in the Land, yet) very much of the fruit of their labour, by preſerving the doctrine, and all the Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt in their parity, and adding in ſome meaſure thereto the power and life thereof: We do therefore charge all the Miniſters of the Land before God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall judge the quick and the dead at his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in his kingdom, as in every thing to be enſamples of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and to walk without offence, that the Miniſtry be not blamed; ſo <hi>to take heed unto the Flock over which the holy Ghoſt hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them ever-ſeers, to declare unto them all the counſell of God,</hi> and to give them timous warning concerning every danger and duty, and to hold forth unto them the ſolid grounds of reall comforlation, by which they may be encouraged and comforted in all their tryals and afflictions, that they may be free of the blood of all men, and have this as a ground of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, even the teſtimony of their conſciences, that in ſimplicity and godly pureneſs, not with fleſhly wiſdom, but by the grace of God they have had their converſation in the world, and have exhorted and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, and charged every one committed unto them, as a Father doth his children; eſpecially, Miniſters ought to be carefull to be much in diſcovering the temptations, and preſſing the duties of the times, that thoſe who are under their charge may know what to avoyd, and what to imbrace and purſue. If all the Watchmen in the Land ſhall give warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and blow the Trumpet at once, it ſhall not be eaſie for enemies to prey upon the people of God: We know no cauſe why any whom God hath called to preach the Goſpel, ſhould be affraid to ſpeak boldly in the Name of the Lord, ſince God hath given ſo manifeſt a teſtimony of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> care and protection in preſerving them theſe yeers paſt, who have ſtriven to be faithfull to him who hath called them from all the fury and malice of the haters of the work of God, and of the Kingdom of his Son Jeſus Chriſt, who hath promiſed to be with his ſervants unto the end of the world.</p>
            <p>Albeit the Land be involved in many difficulties, and compaſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with great and imminent dangers; yet there is hope and ground of conſolation concerning this thing; the Lord is in the midſt of us, and we are called by his name, our ears hear the joyfull ſound of the Goſpel, and our eyes ſee our Teachers. We behold the arm of the Lord ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out daily in working ſalvation for his people, and anſwering their deſires upon their enemies, by terrible things in righteouſneſs; although
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117692:9"/>we be but few in number, yet the Lord of Hoſts is with us, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the power of his ſtrength we ſhall be able to prevail; although our Land be filled with ſin, yet we have not been forſaken of the Lord our God, but he hath always had compaſſion upon us, and delivered us in all our diſtreſſe; although ſome of underſtanding fall, it is but to try, and to purge, and to make white even to the end, becauſe it is yet for a time appointed; although many cleave to us by flatteries, yet there be a rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant who keep their integrity, and the Lord ſhall do good to theſe that be good; but ſuch as turn aſide to crooked ways, ſhall be led forth with the workers of iniquity.</p>
            <p>The Lords people in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> who adhere to the Cauſe and Covenant, may be perplexed, but ſhall not deſpair; they may be perſecuted, but ſhall not be forſaken; they may be caſt down, but ſhall not be deſtroyed; and although uniformity, and the work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in theſe lands ſeem not only to be retarded, but almoſt pluckt up by the roots, and the foundations thereof razed; yet the ſeed which the Lord hath ſown there, ſhall again take root downward, and bear fruit upward; The zeal of the Lord of Hoſts ſhall perform this.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
